<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Programming Pilgrim</title>
    <link>https://markuspg.github.io/</link>
    <description>Recent content on Programming Pilgrim</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution ShareAlike 4.0 International License.</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Sat, 22 Jul 2023 18:02:45 +0200</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://markuspg.github.io/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Technik Museum Speyer</title>
      <link>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/technik_museum_speyer/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 22 Jul 2023 18:02:45 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/technik_museum_speyer/</guid>
      <description>Recently I had the special joy of visiting one of my favourite museums again after I guess about 15 years - the Technik Museum Speyer. For me as a computer guy it&amp;rsquo;s a welcome diversion to see and study something physical instead of just immaterial thoughts and ideas.
With this post I want to give a concise overview of the hightlights of the vast and varied collection of the museum.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>A praise of conservative dependency handling</title>
      <link>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/conservative_dependencies/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 29 Apr 2023 18:46:11 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/conservative_dependencies/</guid>
      <description>Currently I work on porting GnoTime from deprecated dependencies on Gnome 2 into the modern era. The last &amp;ldquo;feature commit&amp;rdquo; before the refactoring was in 2013 - so the dependencies are quite ancient. Likewise the build system is good old GNU Autotools. So apart of upgrading the dependencies porting the build to a more modern build system would be a worthwhile effort. For my own projects I try to keep the dependencies compatible to current Debian oldstable, but during refactoring I prefer to use the most recent tooling available.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Disassembling my TUXEDO Computers InfinityBook Pro 15 v4</title>
      <link>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/clevo_n15xzu_teardown/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Apr 2022 22:35:13 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/clevo_n15xzu_teardown/</guid>
      <description>Unfortunately my InfinityBook Pro 15 v4 from TUXEDO Computers GmbH recently got dropped badly twice. After the second drop the screen was flickering at best or not working at all. This made me attempt to disassemble it to try to fix the screen. The barebone is a N15xZU from Clevo. The sticker on the underside can be seen below:
At first I loosened all screws on the underside. The red and the yellow one are particularly important, since these are required to lift the keyboard in the next step.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Completed Project: patir</title>
      <link>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/completed_project_patir/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 22 Jun 2021 21:37:52 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/completed_project_patir/</guid>
      <description>Recently I resolved to (try to) abstain from starting new programming projects before having finished the current ones.
The first fruit of this resolution is a refactoring of patir, a Ruby gem I use for a project at work. My contributions mostly come down to:
 extending the coverage of its unit tests increasing its documentation&amp;rsquo;s coverage to 100% introducing RuboCop to the project and realizing a common style and adherence to best practises updating the gem&amp;rsquo;s dependencies to their current versions  </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Flashing with uuu from within a QEMU Hosted Linux VM</title>
      <link>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/uuu_within_vm/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 28 Jul 2020 22:19:37 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/uuu_within_vm/</guid>
      <description>For my current work project I have to integrate flashing a NXP i.MX8 from a virtual machine running Ubuntu Focal Fossa (20.04) on top of a QEMU hypervisor on a Proxmox 6.1 host. The flash process is done with the uuu tool from NXPmicro.
Unfortunately the initial flashing attempts were not successful. After quite a few tries a pattern crystallized. The very first flashing attempt after rebooting the VM and resetting the i.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Regularly used QEMU invocations</title>
      <link>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/qemu_commands/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 18 Jul 2020 14:34:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/qemu_commands/</guid>
      <description>This post is nothing more than a quick reference of QEMU commands for different scenarios.
Virtual Machine Image Creation A command to create an image:
qemu-img create -f qcow2 -o nocow=on TestClient.img 64G  The -o nocow=on option is valid on Btrfs only and shall avoid degraded performance.
Installing and Running the Guest Operating System The image can then be installed and run with:
qemu-system-x86_64 -cdrom Downloads/debian-10.4.0-amd64-netinst.iso -enable-kvm -hda TestClient.img -k de -m 4096 -name &#39;Test Server&#39;  The -cdrom part is only passed on installation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Building Android Pie on Debian Buster</title>
      <link>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/aosp_pie_with_debian_buster/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 09 Apr 2020 17:24:56 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/aosp_pie_with_debian_buster/</guid>
      <description>Until now I was falling back to Debian 9 &amp;ldquo;Stretch&amp;rdquo; for compiling the Android Open Source Project. This was due to the fact that compiling Android 8.1 &amp;ldquo;Oreo&amp;rdquo; failed to compile on Debian 10 &amp;ldquo;Buster&amp;rdquo; for me.
My most recent project is based on Android 9 &amp;ldquo;Pie&amp;rdquo; and for this reason I wanted to give Debian Buster a new shot. And indeed - it worked! I conducted a network install with the netinst installation medium installing only the base utilities as additional components in the task selector.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Compiling A More Recent Python Version On Debian Stretch</title>
      <link>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/compiling_python_on_debian/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 27 Mar 2020 13:26:29 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/compiling_python_on_debian/</guid>
      <description>For a current work project I&amp;rsquo;m again dealing with building and modifying the Android Open Source Project. As usual my operating system of choice for that task is Debian Stretch (9.12).
Since my last Android builds Google&amp;rsquo;s repo tool for organizing the multitude of repositories that are needed for an Android build got finally updated from Python 2 to Python 3 (and that seemingly straight to Python 3.6).
Therefore on every invocation of repo init I got a complaint about an incompatible Python version being used (it still worked, but who does not like resolving error messages?</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Quick AOSP Build</title>
      <link>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/quick_aosp/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Oct 2019 20:46:54 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/quick_aosp/</guid>
      <description>This is an attempt at trying out how fast AOSP can be built for a Nexus 5X from scratch including setting up a virtual machine with Debian Stretch in which the build will be done. For virtualization VMware Workstation 15 Player was used on a Windows 10 v1809 running on a DELL laptop with an Intel Core i9-8950HK and 32 GB RAM (eight virtual cores and 16 GB of RAM were allocated to the VM).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>(Re-)Installing a HP LaserJet P1606dn</title>
      <link>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/hp1606dn/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 17 Oct 2019 17:45:23 +0200</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://markuspg.github.io/posts/hp1606dn/</guid>
      <description>As about every two years I upgraded my mother&amp;rsquo;s computer to the newest Debian release. This time from Stretch to Buster (thanks to the Debian community for this great release again!).
For years I bought HP printers because they worked really nice with Linux. Last I bought a HP LaserJet P1606dn. This one harmed the Linux happiness. It needs some binary plugin and this regularly is a pain to install.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
